Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at some new research
on one of our favorite beverages
and we start with how to
choose the healthiest coffee.
Coffee may have beneficial
effects on inflammation,
lung function, insulin
sensitivity, and depression.
This may be in part because of a
class of polyphenol phytonutrients
found in coffee beans called chlorogenic
acids, proven to have favorable effects
with studies like these where
they just give it alone in pill form
and can show beneficial effects, such as
acute blood pressure-lowering activity,
dropping the top and bottom blood pressure
numbers within hours of consumption.
OK, so which coffee has the most?
We know how to choose the reddest tomato,
the deepest orange sweet potato,
since many of the plant pigments
are the antioxidants themselves.
How do you choose
the healthiest coffee?
More than a hundred coffees were tested,
and different coffees had different
caffeine levels, but the chlorogenic
acid levels varied by more than 30-fold.
As a consequence, coffee selection
may have a large influence
on the potential health
potential of coffee intake.
So all those studies that show that
one cup of coffee does this or that,
what does that even mean
when coffee can vary so greatly?
Interestingly, the major
contributor to the wide range
was the coffee
purchased from Starbucks,
which had an extremely
low chlorogenic acid content,
averaging 10 times
lower than the others.
Maybe it's because they
roast their beans too dark.
The more you roast,
the less there is.
They appear to be partially
destroyed by roasting.
Caffeine is pretty stable, but a dark
roast may wipe out nearly 90%
of the chlorogenic acid
content of the beans.
The difference between a medium
light roast and a medium roast
was not enough though to make a
difference in total antioxidant status
in people's bloodstreams
after drinking them;
they both gave about
the same boost.
Other factors, such as how
you prepare it or decaffeination,
don't appear to have a major effect.
What about adding milk?
Long-time fans may remember
this ancient video,
where the addition of milk was shown
to prevent the protective effects
of tea on artery function.
Drink black tea and you get
a significant improvement
in vascular function within hours,
whereas addition of milk completely
blunted the effects of tea.
Here's the big boost in artery
function you get drinking tea,
but drink the same amount
of tea with milk and it's like
you never drank the tea at all.
They think it's the casein to blame,
one of the milk proteins binding
up the tea phytonutrients.
Bottom-line, this finding that the tea-
induced improvement in vascular function
is completely attenuated after addition
of milk may have broad implications
on the mode of tea preparation
and consumption.
In other words, maybe we should not add
milk to tea or put cream on our berries.
It appears to have the same effect
on berry phytonutrients, or chocolate.
Check this out.
Eat milk chocolate,
and nothing much happens
to the antioxidant power
of your bloodstream.
But eat dark chocolate and get a nice
spike within an hour of consumption.
Yeah, but is that just because
the milk in milk chocolate
crowds out some of the
antioxidant-rich cocoa?
Milk chocolate may
only be like 20% cocoa,
whereas a good dark chocolate may
be like 70% or more cocoa solids.
No, it's not just that.
Here's how much of this
cocoa phytonutrient
you get into your bloodstream
eating dark chocolate
compared to milk chocolate.
But eat that same amount
of dark chocolate
with a glass of milk and
it blocks about half.
OK, that's cocoa beans;
what about coffee beans?
When milk was added to
the coffee in like a test tube,
antioxidant activity decreased by more
than half with just a splash of milk,
and down like 95% in latte
or something with lots of milk.
OK, but what happens in a test tube
doesn't necessarily happen in a person.
I mean, you don't know
until you put it to the test.
And indeed, over the course of a day
significantly fewer chlorogenic acids
made it into people's bloodstreams
drinking coffee with milk
compared to black, cutting
absorption by more than half.
What about soymilk?
In a test tube, coffee phytonutrients do
appear to bind not only to dairy proteins
but also egg and soy proteins.
You can see how they did
this computer modeling
showing how these coffee compounds
can dock inside the nooks and crannies
of dairy, egg white, and soy proteins,
but what happens in a test
tube or a computer simulation
doesn't necessarily
happen in a person.
Eggs haven't been put to the test,
so you don't know if having omelets
with your black coffee
could impair absorption,
and neither has soymilk until now.
Yeah, either way soymilk has some
inherent benefits over cow's milk,
but does it have the same
nutrient blocking effects?
And the answer is no.
No significant difference in the
absorption of coffee phytonutrients
drinking coffee black or with soymilk.
What seemed to be happening
is that the soy proteins
do initially bind the coffee compounds
up in the small intestine,
but then your good bacteria
can release them so they can be
absorbed down in the lower intestine.
So considering the reversible nature of
binding as opposed to the dairy proteins,
it seems not to be as relevant as
to whether or not you add soy milk.
In our next story,
we explore why coffee may
not be for everyone.
Three-quarters of American
adults drink coffee,
about half of which
on a daily basis.
That comes out to a million
tons of coffee every year.
Might there be "grounds" for concern?
Population studies have found
that coffee drinkers tend to have
lower risk of Parkinson's, less prostate
cancer (especially the women),
less liver cancer, less diabetes, liver
cirrhosis, depression among women,
and a reduction in mortality overall, such
that coffee drinkers tend to live longer
than non-coffee drinkers, with mortality
bottoming out at about four cups a day.
But these are all just associations.
You don't know if it's cause and
effect until you put it to the test.
For example, coffee really
does seem to protect the liver.
Take people with chronic hepatitis
and have them drink coffee, or not,
for a month, then
switch them back.
And the coffee really
did seem to help.
Similarly, randomize Parkinson's patients
to get two cups of coffee's worth
of caffeine and get a
significant improvement
in movement symptoms
within three weeks.
Runners, randomized to drink coffee,
shaved about six seconds off their mile.
Weight lifters, randomized to
coffee, can squat more weight,
about 600 pounds more worth of reps.
And not just athletic performance.
A cup of coffee's worth of caffeine
can significantly improve IELT,
which stands for "intravaginal
ejaculation latency time,"
from two minutes all
the way up to five.
Unfortunately, those effectively
randomized at birth to genetically
just have a higher
predilection to drink coffee
do not appear to be protected
from diabetes, or depression,
or Alzheimer's, or obesity,
or metabolic syndrome.
So it seems the protective associations
may just be due to confounding factors,
like maybe those who drink coffee just
happen to exercise more or something.
And the same with prostate cancer: no
apparent cause-and-effect relationship,
and even the mortality benefit
seemed to disappear.
Even if a study did show
coffee drinking could
extend lifespan by reducing
inflammation or improving
lung function, or insulin sensitivity,
that would mean on average.
There is "inter-individual variability"
after consumption
of major plant-food compounds,
meaning people may respond differently.
For example, how crazy is this: in some
rare individuals, heavy use of caffeine
apparently provokes sleepiness.
That's an extreme example.
Most of the time it's just that some
individuals may benefit more than others
from the health effects
of different foods.
For example, because of differences in gut
bacteria, only a minority of Westerners
may derive extra benefit from soy,
as I've described before.
The most common difference in caffeine
effects is that, while most people
metabolize caffeine rapidly, certain
gene variants in liver detox enzymes
make some people slow metabolizers.
Might that make a difference?
Well, habitual coffee consumption
of at least three cups a day
has been associated with uncontrolled
blood pressure among older individuals
diagnosed with hypertension,
suggesting that moderating
coffee intake may be a
good idea for some people.
But even if it was cause-and-effect,
that would be on average.
What would happen if you split people up
by how fast they metabolize caffeine?
Compared to coffee abstainers, those who
have impaired caffeine metabolism genes
have an elevated risk of becoming
hypertensive at one to three cups a day,
and especially at four or more.
OK, but check this out.
For the rapid metabolizers not
only was there no excess risk
at one to three cups, heavy coffee
drinkers were protected,
meaning apparently
the more coffee they drank,
the lower their risk.
How do we explain that?
Coffee is a complex blend of a vast
number of different compounds.
There are protective polyphenol
antioxidants that are beneficial.
Coffee beans are, after all, beans—
well, actually, seeds, but
seeds are really healthy too.
On the other hand, there's the caffeine,
which can spike adrenaline levels
in the blood, but only if
you're a slow metabolizer.
Rapid metabolizers can
clear caffeine so fast
that there's no increase in adrenaline
even at four or more cups a day.
And so then you just have the
beneficial polyphenols that actually
lower your blood pressure,
hence the benefit overall.
Thus, there seems to be a
Jekyll and Hyde aspect to coffee
whose overall action on the
cardiovascular system appears
to be regulated by that
gene for the enzyme
that metabolizes caffeine.
The important question, though, is
does it give women larger breasts?
W-h-a-t?
Young women who drink a lot of coffee
and are rapid caffeine metabolizers
have about a half-a-baseball-sized
larger breast volume, which may be
a bad thing as breast volume is
associated with breast cancer risk.
But no, the important question is
what about heart attack risk?
In slow metabolizers, daily coffee
consumption appeared to double
the odds of a heart attack, or even
quadruple the odds at four cups a day,
whereas in the rapid caffeine
metabolizers, daily coffee consumption
was protective, cutting the odds of
a heart attack by more than half,
or at least until you get up
to four or more cups a day.
The protective effects observed
among rapid metabolizers suggest
that the efficient elimination of
caffeine might have unmasked
the protective effects of other
phytochemicals in coffee.
We think it may be
the adrenaline again,
since if you're a slow metabolizer of
adrenaline, high coffee consumption
may put you at risk as well.
So, is coffee friend or foe?
These studies suggest the possibility
that slow caffeine metabolizers
who consume caffeinated coffee
may have an increased risk
of cardiovascular disease,
whereas fast caffeine metabolizers
may be protected from this risk
by the antioxidants and other
beneficial compounds present.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.